Ludlow mss., 1898-1948 LMC 1842
Lilly Library
Ludlow mss.
1898-1948
Lilly Library
Ludlow, Louis, 1873-1950.
LMC 1842
35 Boxes 23 standard, 12 custom
The Ludlow mss., 1898-1948, consists of the papers of Louis Leon Ludlow, 1873-1950, journalist and congressman from Indiana.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 1954, 1963, 1964
Biographical Note
Louis Leon Ludlow, 1873-1950, was a journalist and congressman from Indiana. He was born on a farm in Fayette County, Indiana on June 24, 1873, the son of Henry Louis and Isabelle (Smiley) Ludlow. In 1892, after graduating from Connersville High School, Ludlow moved to Indianapolis to work as a reporter for the Indianapolis Sun and then the Indianapolis Sentinel and the Indianapolis Press. He became a Washington correspondent for several newspapers in Indiana and Ohio. His wife, Katherine Huber of Irvington, Indiana, worked as the society editor for the Indianapolis Sentinel. They were married on September 17, 1896. From 1901 to 1929, Ludlow worked in the Congressional Press Galleries. He was elected as a Democrat to the 71st Congress in 1928, representing Indiana's 7th district. He served ten consecutive terms before retiring in 1948. Ludlow is best known for his efforts to pass the Ludlow Amendment, a proposed amendment to the Constitution which called for a national referendum on any declaration of war by Congress, except in cases of a direct attack on the United States. Despite widespread support for the amendment, it failed to pass. After retiring from his career as a lawmaker, Ludlow resumed his work as a newspaper correspondent until his death on November 28, 1950. He is buried in Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The Correspondence series includes letters introducing Ludlow as Washington representative of the Indianapolis Sentinel, 1901; letters congratulating him on his transfer to Washington correspondent of the George F. McCulloch's chain of papers, the Indianapolis Star, the Muncie Star, and the Terre Haute Star, 1903; a tribute to Colonel Charles A. Lindbergh, 1927; letters and articles on Indian mounds in Indiana and Ohio, 1928; and letters from the 1930s on Townsend's old age pension plan.
Correspondence also includes letters and petitions on the Peace Amendment which proposed to amend the Constitution of the United States to provide for a referendum vote on war and to take the profit out of war, 1935-1940. Presidents of universities and colleges, ministers, religious organizations, railroad brotherhoods, other labor organizations, American Association of University Women, the League of Women Voters, American War Mothers, National Grange, Women's Christian Temperance Union, business and professional women's clubs, peace organizations, prominent men and women in all professions, and the common people all supported the amendment. In spite of numerous letters from congressmen and senators to vote for the bill, it was defeated. Letters of regret from the rank and file followed the announcement of the vote.
Included are also letters congratulating Ludlow on receiving an honorary LLD from Butler University in 1940; letters regretting his decision not to stand for re-election to Congress in 1948; and copies of two letters September 14 and November 10, 1839, from Charles Mayer, founder of Charles Mayer & Co. of Indianapolis, to friends in Germany giving an account of his voyage from Germany to Baltimore, his trip from Baltimore to Cincinnati, and his first jobs in Cincinnati and Indianapolis.
Printed materials include unbound clippings and two printed publications.
The Scrapbooks series contains newspaper clippings of articles and speeches by Ludlow, articles about him, and articles of interest to him; pictures; pamphlets; leaflets; and press releases. They are organized into subseries as follows: numbered scrapbooks, 31 volumes and two volumes of index, 1863-1948; scrapbooks of material relating to Ludlow's efforts for a constitutional amendment giving the electorate the right to vote on U.S. participation in foreign wars, eight numbered volumes and one index volume, 1923-1948; four unnumbered scrapbooks of clippings, Nov. 1901-Mar. 1903, Jan.-July, 1913 and 1927-1928. The first three unnumbered scrapbooks contain clippings of newspaper articles by Ludlow. In addition to the indexes for the first two series of scrapbooks, there are three scrapbook indexes on cards as follows: a subject index, a title index, and an index by names of newspapers.
Writings includes bound typescripts of two of Ludlow's publications, In the Heart of Hoosierland: A Story of the Pioneers, Based on Many Actual Experiences (1925) and Hell or Heaven (1937).
Note on Indexing Term - "Law": Among the papers are letters and petitions on the Peace Amendment which proposed to amend the Constitution of the United States to provide for a referendum vote on war and to take the profit out of war, 1935-1940.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Printed; III. Scrapbooks; and IV. Writings.
Legislators --Indiana --Archives.; Legislators --Indiana --Correspondence.; Women's rights.; United States --Foreign relations --Treaties.; Indiana --Politics and government --1929-1933.; Indiana --Politics and government --1933-1953.; United States --Politics and government --1929-1933.; United States --Politics and government --1933-1953.; Indiana--Politics and government; International relations; Law; United States—Politics and government—20th century; World War, 1939-1945; Ludlow, Louis, 1873-1950.; Ludlow, Louis, 1873-1950. --Correspondence.
- Correspondence
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondents represented in the collection include:
  George Ade
  Arthur William Aleshire
  Truman Hudson Alexander
  Devere Allen
  Robert Gray Allen
  Thomas Ryum Amlie
  Charles Arthur Anderson
  August Herman Andresen
  William Sumner Appleton
  William Albert Ashbrook
  Henry Avery Atkinson
  John Miller Baer
  Henry Horneman Bagger
  Newton Diehl Baker
  Frank Washington Ballou
  William Brockman Bankhead
  Alben William Barkeley
  Hugh Arthur Barnhart
  Edward P. Barry
  William Bernard Barry
  Bruce Barton
  Arthur R. Baxter
  Charles Jasper Bell
  Ira Elbert Bennett
  Allan Louis Benson
  William Markle Berlin
  Albert Jeremiah Beveridge
  Frederick Elliott Biermann
  Herbert Seely Bigelow
  William Frederick Bigelow
  Charles Gustav Binderup
  Edgar BlakeSchuyler Otis Bland
  Thomas Lindsay Blanton
  Gerald John Boileau
  Stephen Bolles
  Chester Castle Bolton
  Sirus Orestes Bond
  Homer Truett Bone
  William Judson Boone
  Lyle H. Boren
  Claude Gernade Bowers
  Paul Haynes Bowman
  Lewis Leonard Boyer
  John Joseph Boylan
  Arthur Braden
  Sophonisba Preston Breckinridge
  Ralph Owen Brewster
  Abraham Lincoln Brick
  Joseph Broadman
  Erica May Brooks
  Joshua Twing Brooks
  Robert Clarkson Brooks
  Hilton Ultimus Brown
  William Frank Brunner
  William Lowe Bryan
  John Jenkins Buchanan
  Paul Henry Buchholz
  Richard Thompson Buckler
  Charles Anthony Buckley
  Raymond Leslie Buell
  Robert Johns Bulkley
  Usher Lloyd Burdick
  George Burnham
  Nicholas Murray Butler
  Smedley Darlington Butler
  Richard Evelyn Byrd
  Samuel Parkes Cadman
  Clarence Cannon
  Arthur Capper
  Charles Alexander Capron
  Frank Carlson
  Lawrence Edward Carlson
  Francis Higbee Case
  Williams Richards Castle
  Samuel McCrea Cavert
  Emanuel Celler
  Walter Clift Chandler
  Theodore Christianson
  William Michael Citron
  Raymond Clapper
  Bennett Champ Clark
  David Worth Clark
  John Hessin Clarke
  Jefferson Helm Claypool
  John Joseph Cochran
  Harry Buffington Coffee
  Charles Emmet Coffin
  Charles L. Coffin
  Hymen Ezra Cohen
  Charles J. Colden
  William Purrington Cole
  George William Coleman
  William Meyers Colmer
  Edgar Thomas Conley
  William Patrick Connery
  Calvin Coolidge
  Charles Edward Coughlin
  William Ben Cravens
  Fred Lewis Crawford
  Luigi Criscuolo
  George Washington Cromer
  Charles Noel Crosby
  Robert Crosser
  André Crotti
  Eugene Burgess Crowe
  Fred Nelson Cummings
  Jesse Lee Cuninggim
  George Albert Cunningham
  Michael Joseph Curley
  Max Cohen Currick
  John Burrwood Daly
  Josephus Daniels
  Colgate Whitehead Darden
  Elmer Homes Davis
  James John Davis
  William Prentice Dearing
  Washington Strother Dearmont
  Peter Joseph DeMuth
  William Cullen Dennis
  Henry J. Derthick
  Dorothy Detzer
  Charles Elmer Dietrich
  Everett McKinley Dirksen
  John William Ditter
  Alvin Victor Donahey
  Arthur Jerome Drossaerts
  Warren Joseph Duffey
  James Patrick Bernard Duffy
  Matthew Anthony Dunn
  William Crapo Durant
  Winfield Taylor Durbin
  John Napier Dyer
  Charles Aubrey Eaton
  Kerr Eby
  Chalres Richard Eckert
  David Morton Edwards
  John Rogers Edwards
  Clark Mell Eichelberger
  Henry Ellenbogen
  Edward Charles Elliott
  Wade Hampton Ellis
  Robert Erskine Ely
  James Ozro Engleman
  Luther Harris
  Marcellus Hugh Evan
  Frank Diehl Fackenthal
  Charles I. Faddis
  Charles Warren Fairbanks
  James Indus Farley
  William Burton Farmer
  Harlan Luther Feeman
  Phillip Colgan Gerguson
  Simeon Davison Fess
  Morris Marcus Feuerlicht
  Orien Wesley Fifer
  George W. Finnup
  William Joseph Fitzgerald
  Frank Bates Flanner
  Thomas Brooks Fletcher
  Benjamin Kurtz Focht
  Oscar G. Foellinger
  Michael E. Foley
  Aime Joseph Forand
  Leland Merritt Ford
  William Fortune
  James Archibald Frear
  James Edward Freeman
  Ludwig Ernest Fuerbrigner
  Hampton Pitts Fulmer
  Joseph Hall Fussell
  John Clinton Futrall
  Harry Morehouse Gage
  Linn Abel Easton Gale
  Zona Gale
  Frank Ernest Gannett
  Bernard John Gehrmann
  Newton Whiting Gilbert
  James Hilary Gildea
  Guy Mark Gillette
  George W. Gillie
  Thomas Alan Goldsborough
  Israel Goldstein
  Irby J. Good
  James Putnam Goodrich
  Frank Porter Graham
  James Richard Grant
  W. Edward J. Gratz
  Cary Travers Grayson
  Robert Alexis Green
  William Green
  Arthur Herbert Greenwood
  W. J. Greenwood
  Otto Gresham
  James Aloysius Griffin
  Glenn Griswold
  William Anderson Guthrie
  John William Gwynne
  Delbert James Haff
  Maurice Stewart Hague
  Charles Abraham Halleck
  William Andrew Hanley
  James Franklin Hanly
  Ole Hanson
  Mrs. Florence (Kling) Harding
  Samuel Ralph Harlow
  Vincent Francis Harrington
  Julian LaRose Harris
  Russell Benjamin Harrison
  Franck Roberts Havenner
  Luther Newton Hayes
  William Harrison Hays
  Walter Dutton Head
  Arthur Daniel Healey
  Thomas Henry Healy
  William Randolph Hearst
  Robert D. Heinl
  James Alexander Hemenway
  Frank Earl Hering
  William Emil Hess
  William Lincoln Higgins
  Fred Herman Hildebrandt
  Charles Lewis Hill
  Knute Hill
  James Noah Hillman
  Richmond Pearson Hobson
  John Henry Hoeppel
  Clare Eugene Hoffman
  Harold Giles Hoffman
  Harry Vance Holloway
  John Haynes Holmes
  Hamilton Holt
  Rush Dew Holt
  John Walbon Holtzman
  Herbert Hoover
  John Edgar Hoover
  Clifford Ragsdale Hope
  Alanson Bigelow Houghton
  John Mills Houston
  Roy Wilson Howard
  Timothy Edward Howard
  Louis McHenry How
  Cordell Hull
  Merlin Hull
  Walter Hullihen
  R. C. Hutchinson
  Edward L. Israel
  Edouard Victor Michel Izac
  Bernhard Martin Jacobsen
  William Darius Jamieson
  Benjamin Jarrett
  Mrs. Virginia (Ellis) Jenckes
  Arthur Byron Jenks
  Albert Johnson
  Dewey William Johnson
  Fred Bates Johnson
  George William Johnson
  Oscar John Johnson
  Carl A. Jones
  Frederick A. Joss
  William Alexander Julian
  Edmund George Kaufman
  Leroy J. Keach
  Edward Keating
  Helen Adams Keller
  James Albert Keller
  Frank Billings Kellogg
  Edward Austin Kelly
  George Bradshaw Kelly
  John Bailey Kelly
  Joseph Patrick Kennedy
  Edward Aloysius Kenney
  Raymond Asa Kent
  Paul Bentley Kern
  John Hosea Kerr
  Frederick Doyle Kershner
  Mrs. Isabella (Selmes) King
  Willard Monroe Kiplinger
  John C. Kirch
  Frank Le Blond Kloeb
  Harold Knutson
  Herman Paul Kopplemann
  Otto Edward Kriege
  Barend Herman Kroeze
  Philip Fox LaFollette
  William Purnell Lambertson
  William Langer
  William Henry Larrabee
  Benjamin Frnaklin Lawrence
  Emmanuel B. Ledvina
  Joshua Bryan Lee
  Wallace Orison Lee
  Rudolph Gaar Leeds
  William Lemke
  Frederick Lent
  Adna Wright Leonard
  Salmon Oliver Levinson
  John Llewellyn Lewis
  Lawrence Lewis
  Frederick Joseph Libby
  Albert Lieber
  Richard Lieber
  Eli Lilly
  Arthur West Little
  Frank Leslie Littleton
  Wesley Lloyd
  George Browning Lockwood
  Marvel Mills Logan
  Augustine Lonergan
  Irwin Jacob Lubbers
  Robert Luce
  Henry Carl Luckey
  John Frederick Luecke
  Ernest Lundeen
  Charles Jackson Lynn
  William Gibbs McAdoo
  James McAndrews
  Douglas MacArthur
  John Little McClellan
  John William McCormack
  Roy McCuskey
  John S. McFaddin
  John Steven McGroarty
  Raymond Stephen McKeough
  E. Kirk McKinney
  Charles Francis McLaughlin
  Floyd Ivan McMurray
  John Gilbert McNutt
  Chester Amos McPheeters
  John Jackson McSwain
  Mrs. Luella Frances (Smith) McWhirter
  Warren Grant Magnuson
  Verner Wright Main
  Clarence E. Manion
  Vito Marcantonio
  George Joseph Marott
  Daniel Lash Marsh
  Edison Marshall
  Mrs. Lois I. (Kimsey) Marshall
  Thomas Riley Marshall
  Earle Martin
  John Andrew Martin
  Samuel Chapman Massingale
  Willfred Otto Mauck
  Maury Maverick
  George Willard Maxwell
  Augustus Kiefer Mayer
  Charles Mayer
  James Michael Mead
  Henry Louis Mencken
  Matthew Joseph Merritt
  Earl Cory Michener
  Frederick A. Miller
  Raphael Harwood Miller
  Sherman Minton
  John Fowler Mitchell
  John Ridley Mitchell
  Benjamin Baker Boeur
  Joseph Patrick Monaghan
  Andrew Jackson Montague
  Fred Atkins Moore
  Robert Walton Moore
  Arthur Ernest Morgan
  Joy Elmer Morgan
  John Mary Morin
  Theodore Leo Moritz
  Frank Morrison
  Samuel E. Morss
  James Wheaton Mott
  Orrice Abram Murdock
  Marvin Murphy
  Thomas William Nadal
  George Williston Nash
  Harry Turner Newcomb
  Harry Whinna Nice
  Meredith Nicholson
  James William Noel
  Stephen Croan Noland
  Gerald Prentice Nye
  George Donoghue O'Brien
  Robert Lincoln O'Brien
  Jerry J. O'Connell
  Caleb W. O'Connor
  James Francis O'Connor
  John Joseph O'Connor
  Mrs. Caroline Love (Goodwin) O'Day
  John Callan O'Laughlin
  James Aloysius O'Leary
  James Churchill Oliver
  Edward Asbury O'Neal
  Emmet O'Neal
  Edward Leo O'Neil
  John Francis O`Ryan
  Frank Ostman
  Jesse Overstreet
  Garfield Bromley Oxnam
  Albert George Parker
  Fletcher Douglas Parker
  Wright Patman
  Edward White Patterson
  George Campbell Peery
  Claude Denson Pepper
  John Joseph Pershing
  Ralph L. Peters
  James Hardin Peterson
  Samuel Barrett Pettengill
  Alfred Noroton Phillips
  Walter Marcus Pierce
  Atlee Pomerene
  Daniel Alfred Poling
  James Gould Polk
  Talcott Williams Powell
  Harry Otis Pritchard
  Harold Scott Quigley
  Homer Price Rainey
  Julian Carven Ralston
  Samuel Moffett Ralston
  Jennings Randolph
  Jeannette Rankin
  Harry Clay Ransley
  Samuel Taliaferro Rayburn
  Ben Rebhuhn
  Edward Herbert Rees
  Charles Frederick Remy
  Robert Rice Reynolds
  Robert Fleming Rich
  William Emanuel Richardson
  Oscar Wetherhold Riegel
  Leonard Riggleman
  Albert Cabell Ritchie
  Joseph Elmer Ritter
  William Cannon Rivers
  David Brown Robertson
  James McClellan Robinson
  John Marshall Robsion
  Mrs. Edith (Nourse) Rogers
  Will Rogers
  Frederick William Roman
  Mrs. Nellie (Tayloe) Ross
  John Augustine Ryan
  Oswald Ryan
  Adolph Joseph Sabath
  Albert Sahm
  Morgan Gurley Sanders
  Joseph Schrembs
  Henry Frederick Schricker
  William Theodore Schulte
  Byron Nicholson Scott
  George Nicholas Seger
  Adolph Seidensticker
  Frank Maryl Setzler
  James Andrew Shanley
  Thomas Hall Shastid
  Avery Albert Shaw
  Henry Clyde Shetrone
  Thomas Roerty Shipp
  Joel Buell Shomaker
  Kenneth Charles Morton Sills
  William Irving Sirovich
  Frederick James Sisson
  Joseph Richard Sizoo
  William Adams Slade
  Henry Lester Smith
  Martin Fernard Smith
  John Buell Snyder
  Mordecai Soltes
  Edmund Davison Soper
  Mary Ellis South
  Charles Robert Sowder
  William Gear Spencer
  Mrs. Flora (Langerman) Spiegelberg
  George Washington Steele
  Karl StefanJames Rauch Stein
  Mrs. Estelle (Miller) Sternberger
  Edward Reilly Stettinius
  James Stacy Stevens
  John B. Stoll
  John Edgar Stoner
  James Arthur Stuart
  Henry Elbert Stubbs
  Reginald H. Sullivan
  John William Summers
  Hatton William Sumners
  Philip Allen Swartz
  Martin Leonard Sweeney
  Zachary Taylor Sweeney
  Elias C. Swihart
  John J. Swint
  Guy Jacob Swope
  Louis John Taber
  Charles Phelps Taft
  Booth Tarkington
  Mrs. Susanah (Robinson) Tarkington
  Henry George Teigan
  Elbert Duncan Thomas
  Norman Mattoon Thomas
  Chester Charles Thompson
  Paul Lamont Thompson
  William Hale Thompson
  Lloyd Thurston
  Charles William Tobey
  Edward Howard Todd
  Clyde Anderson Tolson
  John Gillis Townsend
  Park Trammell
  Charles Joseph Turck
  Mell Gilbert Underwood
  Hubert Utterback
  Walter William Van Kirk
  Frederick Van Nuys
  James Edward Van Zandt
  Oswald Garrison Villard
  Horace Jerry Voorhis
  Robert Ferdinand Wagner
  David Ignatius Walsh
  Francis Eugene Walter
  Otha Donner Wearin
  Zebulon Weaver
  Vincent Wehrle
  Richard Joseph Welch
  Burton Kendall Wheeler
  Compton Ignatius White
  Frank Allan White
  Walter Francis White
  William Allen White
  Alfred Fell Whitney
  Ray Lyman Wilbur
  Clyde Everett Wildman
  Alexander Wiley
  Mrs. Anna (Kelton) Wiley
  Charl Ormond Williams
  Henry Augustus Williams
  Mary Wilhelmine Williams
  Frank Bartlett Willis
  John R. Wilson
  William Henry Wilson
  Otho Winger
  Stephen Samuel Wise
  Gardner Robert Withrow
  Harry Preston Wolfe
  James Wolfenden
  Charles Anderson Wolverton
  Evans Woollen
  Hubert Work
  Whitney S. K. Yeaple
  Archibald Alexander Young
  Consult the Manuscripts Index in the Lilly Library for dates of letters of individual correspondents.
  Arrangement
  The correspondence is arranged in chronological order.
  - 1898 - 1935, May (Box 1)
  - 1935, June - 1937, Mar. (Box 2)
  - 1937, Apr. - 1937, Oct. 27 (Box 3)
  - 1937, Oct. 28 - 1938, Jan. 10 (Box 4)
  - 1938, Jan. 11 - 1939, Apr. (Box 5)
  - 1939, May - 1940, Apr. (Box 6)
  - 1940, May - 1940, Dec. (Box 7)
  - 1941 - 1948 (Box 8)
- Printed
  - Hell or Heaven, by Lewis Ludlow. Stratford, 1937; (1 folder) (Box 8)
  - A Comparison of the Political and Civil Rights of Men and Women in the United States. USGPO, 1936; (1 folder) (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous unbound clippings, (6 folders) (Box 8)
- Scrapbooks
  - Numbered scrapbooks
    - 1901, Nov. 18 - 1902, Nov. 1 (Box 8)
    - 1902, Nov. 21 - 1903, Mar. 27 (Box 8)
    - 1913, Jan. 4 - 1913, July 31 (Box 8)
    - ca. 1924 - 1926 (Box 10)
    - 1927 - 1928 (Box 11)
  - War referendum scrapbooks
    General
    (Oversized items)
    - 1924 - 1937, Feb. (Box 1)
    - 1937, Jan. 5 - Nov. 26 (Box 2)
    - 1937, Nov. 26 - Dec. 22 (Box 3)
    - 1937, Dec. 22 - 1938, Jan. 10 (Box 4)
    - 1938, Jan. 10 - 16 (Box 5)
    - 1938, Jan. 16 - Sept. 25 (Box 6)
    - 1938, Oct. 3 - 1939, May 24 (Box 7)
    - 1939, June - 1948, July (Box 8)
    - Index (Box 9)
  - Scrapbook card indexes
    - Subject index (Box 16)
      - A - Ludlow, office help (Box 16)
      - Ludlow, Patronage - Politics, 2nd campaign, 1930 (Box 17)
      - Prohibition - Z (Box 18)
    - Title index (Box 18)
      - A - Ce (Box 18)
      - Ch - Ludlow attacks (Box 19)
      - Ludlow opens - Sp (Box 20)
      - Sp - Z (Box 21)
    - Newspaper name index (Box 21)
      - A - E (Box 21)
      - F - Indianapolis Star (Box 22)
      - Indianapolis West Side Messenger -Z (Box 23)
- Writings (Box 12)
  - In the Heart of the Hoosier Land., 1924; Bound typescript, with corrections. (Box 12)
  - Hell or Heaven., 1936; Bound typescript, 2 vols., with corrections (Box 12)